What’s the best way
to stay healthy
in the face of so much
conflicting nutrition information?
Well, ideally, you would
go to the source.
The gold standard;
the peer-reviewed
medical literature.
Read through stacks of
the latest medical journals.
But who’s got
time for that?
I do!
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
It’s time for the
Nutrition Facts Grab Bag
where we look at the science
on a wide variety of topics.
Today we start with
the results of a study
that has correlated low calcium intake
and vitamin D exposure
with higher bone fracture rates
in British vegans.
Vegetarians had slightly lower bone
mineral density in their spines.
Although the difference was
basically within the margin of error
for the test, if the bone quality
really is compromised, it could
lead to collapsed vertebrae,
increased spinal fracture risk,
but there's no evidence for this.
The incidence of vertebral fracture
was ascertained in older women
who had been vegan for most of
their lives -- 34 years on average.
And despite their calcium intake
being terrible, about half that
of the nonvegans, and a quarter
of them vitamin D deficient,
the incidence of vertebral fractures
was not significantly different.
Although the vegans had a higher
prevalence of vitamin D deficiency
and lower dietary calcium
intakes, the two factors
were not associated
with bone loss.
In fact, the annual loss in bone
mineral density in the hips
of vegans was less than
half that of the meat eaters,
though the difference did not
reach statistical significance.
Vegetarian women had not been
found to be at higher risk
of any kind of fractures including
wrist fractures in this case,
though among vegetarians,
those who consumed the least
vegetable protein intake were
at the highest risk for fracture.
Those who ate beans every day,
or nuts, or like veggie burgers
only had a third of the wrist fractures
compared to vegetarians
who only ate beans or
other higher protein foods
less than three times a week.
So those that consume a vegan
or vegetarian diet may be
at increased risk of fracture unless
care is taken to ensure an adequate
quantity and variety of foods high
in protein, such as whole grains,
nuts, and beans, split peas,
chickpeas, or lentils are in the diet.
That's one of the reasons
in my free Daily Dozen app
I recommend whole grains
and legumes every day.
Hip fractures are even more
serious. Those eating legumes,
like beans every day, reduced
their risk of hip fracture
by more than 60%, compared to
40% lower risk from meat protein,
with plant-based meats
coming in in between
with about 50% lower
risk of hip fractures.
What's the bottom line
on plant-based diets and
bone health according
to this 2020 review?
Theoretically, a long-term
plant-based diet may reduce
the risk of osteoporosis, but
that has yet to be demonstrated.
What we do know is that
plant-based diets, when ensuring
adequate calcium and vitamin D levels,
don't appear to have any
detrimental effects on bone health.
But this was published August 2020.
In November 2020, the 12-year
follow-up to the study I talked about
in my last video on comparative
fracture risk in vegetarians
versus nonvegetarians
was published, finding that
non-meat eaters, especially vegans,
had higher risks of
total bone fractures,
including at sites associated with
osteoporosis such as hip fractures.
It comes out to be about 20 more
cases in vegans for every 1000
people over 10 years.
So if indeed this is cause-and-effect,
eating vegan there would be
an annual 1 in 500 chance
of having a bone fracture
that you otherwise
might not have had.
Was it because they weren't
eating enough beans?
Apparently not, since
vegans getting more protein
still apparently had higher risk.
Maybe it was because they
weren't getting enough calcium?
Apparently not, since vegans
getting more calcium
still apparently had higher risk.
What about bone and vitamin B12?
If you remember EPIC-Oxford,
where the bone data comes from,
is the same group of British vegans
who had rampant B12 deficiency.
More than half the vegans were
B12 deficient because they
weren't adequately supplementing
with B12 or B12-fortified foods.
This can lead to high
homocysteine levels,
which not only increase stroke risk,
but may increase the
activity of bone-eating cells.
This was in a petri dish, but you do
indeed see low bone mineral density
in those born with a birth defect
that leads to high homocysteine
levels in the blood. Therefore,
high serum homocysteine
may be regarded as a factor
that can reduce both
bone mass and quality,
but you don't know
until you put it to the test.
And homocysteine-lowering
treatment failed to reduce
the risk of bone fracture.
So in the end, the effect of B12
deficiency in bone health
remains to be established.
OK, so how do we explain the higher
fracture rates found among vegans?
The investigators conclude that their
findings suggest that bone health
in vegans requires further research,
but there were some clues.
The elevated fracture risk,
both for total fractures
and for hip fractures specifically,
was only significant for
those under a BMI of 22.5,
which is like under about 130 pounds
for a woman of average height.
So part of the problem is that vegans
tend to be so slender on average.
Why are overweight and obese
individuals protected from fractures?
Well, think about it. They have
cushioning during a fall.
There's more of a
cushion on your hips.
Also, there's an enzyme in fatty
tissue that churns out estrogen,
which is why women increase
their breast cancer risk
a percentage point for every
pound they gain in adulthood.
But estrogen can also have
a bone-preserving effect.
Now you can get the best of both
worlds consuming soy foods,
preventing bone loss while
at the same time associated
with lessening breast
cancer risk for both estrogen
receptor positive tumors and
estrogen receptor negative tumors.
Finally, overweight and obese
individuals may also have
stronger bones just from
the increased weight-bearing.
Carrying 100 extra pounds,
you're doing major
weight bearing exercise
just walking across the room.
So the risk difference they saw
between vegans and meat eaters
were likely at least partially
due to the difference in BMI.
My money, however,
is on vitamin D.
Great Britain is at
Canadian latitudes.
The sun's rays are
at such an angle
during the winter months up there
that the vitamin D levels among
British vegans in the wintertime
drops down to suboptimal levels.
Ideally, we should be up around
75 nanomoles per liter,
or 30 nanograms per milliliter
depending on what units you're using,
which the vegans nail in the summer.
It is the sunshine vitamin after all.
But in the winter, not getting
the vitamin D added to dairy or
found naturally in oily fish, if vegans
aren't supplementing at that latitude
during the winter, their vitamin
D levels may drop too low.
Now randomized controlled trials
show that vitamin D alone
does not seem to
reduce fracture rates,
but boosting people's D and
calcium at the same time does.
So maybe it was a combination of the
relatively low D and calcium intakes
among the vegans that led
to their higher fracture rates.
We won't know for sure
until it's actually put to the test,
and when it is you can be sure
I'll do a video about it.
Did you know that our body
can make vitamin K2
from the K1 in green
leafy vegetables?
Here’s the story.
Vitamin K.
Wait, I know about
vitamins A, B, C, D, and E.
What happened to
vitamins F, G, H, I and J?
It's not alphabetical.
Vitamin K stands for coagulation,
or at least it does in German.
That's the fundamental role vitamin K
plays: helping the blood to clot.
But over the last few decades there's
evidence that it has other roles
in the health of our
bones, heart, and brain.
Kind of reminds me of vitamin D.
We know vitamin D is important
for bone health, but then
there's been all sorts of other
controversial functions ascribed
to it, some of which have been
proven and some disproven.
What about vitamin K?
For bone health, for example,
is the link between vitamin K
and osteoporosis myth or reality?
It turns out the findings on vitamin K
and bone are conflicting and unclear.
It doesn't help that
some of the major trials
were found to be problematic
to say the least, as in...
likely fraudulent,
containing impossible data,
with investigators admitting
to complete fabrication.
And so if you do a systematic
review, eliminating any fraud,
we find no evidence that vitamin K
supplementation affects
bone mineral density
or vertebral fractures.
What about the heart?
Vitamin K supplementation for the
prevention of cardiovascular disease.
There's a vitamin K-activated
protein in your blood
that binds up excess calcium
and helps prevent calcium from
being deposited into the walls
of your arteries and
stiffening them.
So if you give people
extra vitamin K,
will that protect peoples'
arteries from calcification?
It sounds good in theory, but no,
vitamin K does not appear
to consistently prevent progression
of calcification, atherosclerosis,
or arterial stiffness.
For example, artery calcification
is particularly common in patients
with chronic kidney disease, which
can lead to increased artery stiffness,
which is an important risk factor
for heart attacks and strokes.
An earlier trial didn't find any benefit
on coronary artery calcification
between the vitamin K
and placebo groups,
but they were using
kind of a small dose.
So these trials used a whopping
dose daily for a year and... nada.
Vitamin K supplementation did
not improve vascular stiffness
or other measures of artery health.
And in fact, one study on the effect
of vitamin K supplementation
on artery calcification in patients
with diabetes found that
calcification tended to increase
after supplementation
with a type of vitamin K
found in a slimy fermented
soy food called natto.
Now those with higher levels
of vitamin K circulating
in their bloodstreams
do tend to have lower levels
of inflammation, but no wonder.
Where is vitamin K found?
The predominant dietary form
of vitamin K in the
human diet comes from
dark green leafy vegetables
and cruciferous vegetables.
So how did people get
high levels in their blood?
Eating broccoli.
Those with higher levels
of vitamin K in their blood
were eating more
vegetables, less meat.
No wonder they had lower
levels of inflammation.
The recommended adequate daily
intake for vitamin K is set at
70 micrograms a day in Europe,
and between 90 and 120 a day
here in the United States.
Just two leaves of kale has over 70!
And a quarter cup of cooked
kale will get anyone all the K
they need for the day.
Now there is vitamin K
found in meat, dairy and eggs,
averaging about 5 to 10
micrograms per serving.
In other words, they're even
beaten out by iceberg lettuce,
which is mostly water, but still
contains like 2 to 3 times
more vitamin K.
Ah, but that's vitamin K1,
and what's found in animal
products is mostly vitamin K2.
Do you need K2?
Apparently not.
Once you get enough plant-based
K1, there's no established
requirement for K2,
because it hasn't been proven
that K2 has effects
that are different from K1.
They both act the
same way in the body,
thus there's not even enough data
to take K2 into account at all.
So when the recommended
adequate daily intakes are set,
they're only talking about
getting enough K1 from plants,
mostly green vegetables.
In fact most of the bone trials
that flopped used the K2
found in animal products,
and most of the failed heart
studies used K2 as well.
OK, even though there is presently
a lack of randomized trial evidence
to support a beneficial role
for vitamin K in preventing
the worsening of cardiovascular
disease, or bone health,
what if that were to change?
What if all of the sudden K2 was
shown to have unique benefits?
Well, guess what?
The bacteria in your gut make K2.
That's why fermented
foods have K2.
Bacteria make it.
And the bacteria in your gut not
only make it, but it gets absorbed
from your colon up into your system,
contributing a significant amount
of the human vitamin K
requirement, just in case
you miss a couple days of greens.
Vitamin K1 is made by plants
and is the primary dietary form.
Then there are a dozen or so types
of vitamin K2, which are synthesized
by bacteria, including several
types in the human gut.
The exception, though, is a type
of K2 called menaquinone 4, MK4,
which is endogenously
synthesized in mammals
and therefore is found
in animal products.
Now, I don't know if any of you
noticed, but we're mammals, too.
It has consistently been shown
that vitamin K1 from greens is
endogenously converted
inside your body
to the vitamin K2 in animal products.
You're made out of meat, too,
though it took until 2010
before we discovered the human
biosynthetic enzyme that does it.
So no reason at all to take any
sort of vitamin K supplement.
Eat your greens.
In fact when K2 supplements
were looked at, researchers found
significant problems in terms of
contaminants and mislabeling.
Eat your greens.
Now K2 appears in higher
concentrations in certain tissues,
including the brain.
Again, we make K2 from
the K1 we eat in greens,
but maybe extra K2 might help?
Well, if we measure vitamin K
levels in the blood and brains
of centenarians --
those that live over 100 --
concentrations of circulating
K1 from vegetables,
but not cerebral K2,
not the K2 in the brain,
was positively correlated with a
wide range of cognitive measures.
Why?
Likely because they
were eating green vegetables,
and green vegetables
don't just have vitamin K.
Green leafy vegetables are the
most concentrated source of lutein,
the eye health nutrient
that's taken up into the brain
and is associated with cognitive
performance across the life span.
And so in these centenarians,
circulating K1 and lutein
concentrations were
highly correlated,
and so it's hard to tease out exactly
what in greens was so beneficial.
It's like when you see data showing
lower circulating K1 levels in the
blood stream are associated with
increased risk of all-cause mortality,
meaning lower K1 levels were
correlated with a shorter lifespan.
Well, duh.
K1 is found in greens,
and of all the dietary components
correlating with all-cause mortality,
the best evidence appears
to support the intake
of green leafy vegetables and salads
to reduce all-cause mortality.
In other words, eat your greens.
In our final story, we look
at how might we replicate
one of the greatest public health
victories of all time—
the reduction of smoking rates—
but in the field of nutrition.
What we learned from
the tobacco experience,
wrote two preeminent
public health scholars,
is how powerfully profits can
motivate “even at the cost of
millions of lives and
unspeakable suffering.”
“Big Tobacco Played Dirty
and Millions Died.”
How similar is Big Food?
I’ve talked about how
Big Food has used
the same tobacco
industry playbook.
What about using the
anti-tobacco playbook
to counter the obesity crisis?
Tobacco is one of our great
public health victories.
The share of adults who smoke
declined from 42 percent in 1965
down to just 15 percent by 2016.
That’s about 5 out of 12 down
to less than 2 out of 12.
Thanks to the decline,
cigarettes now only kill
about a half million
Americans every year,
whereas our diet now kills
tens of thousands more.
Currently, the leading cause of death
in America is the American diet.
Might we be able to use the same
strategies that were so successful
in the battle against Big Tobacco?
It may be no coincidence
that three of the most
cost-effective policy
interventions against obesity
seem to be taken straight
from the tobacco wars:
(1) taxes on unhealthy products;
(2) front-of-pack labeling; and
(3) a restriction of
advertising to children.
Excise taxes on
cigarettes has been cited
as the single most effective
weapon in slashing smoking rates.
A 25 cents per pack tax to help
deal with some of the societal costs
of smoking was
associated with as much as
a 9 percent decrease
in smoking rates.
The World Health Organization
has estimated
that a 70 percent global
increase in the price could prevent
up to a quarter of all tobacco-
related deaths worldwide.
Extending taxes on alcohol
and tobacco to foodstuffs
was proposed by none
other than Adam Smith
in his 1776 Wealth of Nations:
“Sugar, rum, and
tobacco, are commodities
which are nowhere
necessities of life,
which have become objects of
almost universal consumption,
and which are, therefore, extremely
proper subjects of taxation.”
People have the right to smoke
and drink and eat fattening foods,
the logic goes, but perhaps
they should help defray
some of the publicly-funded
medical costs that result.
Well, if that’s the case, why
not tax obese people directly?
Taxing people based on
their weight was proposed
at least as far back as 1904
in the British Medical Journal,
a kind of pounds-
for-pounds strategy
(actually only up to 7 shillings
and 6 pence per pound).
This was not only to
recompense public coffers,
but nudge behavioral change.
“A tax on fat,” read the proposal,
“would also have an excellent effect
on the health of the nation
by bringing about a reform
of unwholesome habits
of eating and drinking.”
Even a penny-per-ounce tax
on sugar-sweetened beverages
could bring in more
than a billion dollars a year
in states like Texas
and California.
A 10 percent tax on fattening
foods on a national level
could yield a half a
trillion dollars over ten years.
Even if it was combined
with a subsidy that lowered
the cost of fruits and
vegetables by 10 percent,
it would be expected to net
hundreds of billions of dollars.
But would it actually
change people’s habits?
Even a small price
differential (about 10 percent)
between leaded and
unleaded gas was able to shift
the entire auto
industry away from lead.
Could it also shift Americans
to apples from apple pie?
A systematic review of the
available evidence suggests
that dietary financial incentives
and disincentives work.
The cheaper you make
fruits and vegetables,
the more people say they’d buy,
and the more you
tax unhealthy foods,
the lower consumption drops.
Based on this kind of modeling,
a tax on saturated fat—
found mostly in fatty meat,
dairy, and junk—
could potentially save
thousands of lives a year.
But wouldn’t such a tax
disproportionately affect the poor?
Yes, in that we would expect
them to benefit the most!
It’s like cigarette taxes.
The classic tobacco industry
argument is that cigarette taxes
are “unfair” and “regressive,”
burdening the poor the most,
to which the public health community
responded “Cancer is unfair;”
cancer disproportionately
burdens the poor.
So, taxes would be expected to
affect the greatest health gains
for the least well-off.
The fact that the tobacco
industry fought tooth and nail
against cigarette taxes—
everything from
inventing front groups to
overtly buying off politicians—
suggests that taxes can indeed
shift consumption patterns,
but much of the evidence
on changing food behaviors
has not been based
on real-life data.
You can put people through
fancy 3D supermarket simulators
and discover that a 25 percent
discount on fruits and veggies
appears to boost produce
purchasing by the same amount—
up to about two pounds a week.
But virtual vegetables
don’t actually do you any good.
Does this work out
in the real world?
Apparently so.
South Africa’s largest private
health insurer started offering
up to 25 percent cash back
on healthy food purchases
to hundreds of thousands
of households,
up to the U.S. equivalent
of $799 per month.
Why would they give money away?
Because it apparently works—
increasing consumption
of fruits and vegetables
and whole grains,
while at the same time
decreasing the consumption
of foods high in added
salt, sugar, and fat,
including processed
meats and fast food.
Why not just pay people to
lose weight directly?
A systematic review found
11 out of 12 studies
on financial incentives for weight
loss described positive results.
The one that failed to find a benefit
of direct monetary inducements
was only offering $2.80 a day.
With kids, you can get away
with just a nickel or a sticker
to get them to choose
dried fruit over a cookie
as an afterschool snack, though
as soon as the enticements ended,
so did the change in behavior.
Even if the incentives
have to be made permanent,
they might still
pay for themselves.
In the U.S., every dollar spent
taxing processed foods or milk
might net an estimated $2
in healthcare cost savings.
Every dollar spent making
vegetables cheaper could net $3
and subsidizing whole
grains might offer more
than a thousand percent
return on our investment.
Even a 1 percent decrease in the
average price of all fruits and vegetables
might prevent nearly 10,000 heart
attacks and strokes every year.
What about taxes, though, which
tend to be less popular than subsidies?
In Europe, a number of
countries have instituted
taxes on sugary or salty foods,
but Denmark was the first to
introduce a tax on saturated fat.
It only took agribusiness
about a year to squash it,
demonstrating how weak public
health professionals can be
when trying to tackle
corporate power.
This was chalked up to
the “enormous imbalance”
between the political influence exerted
by the public health community
compared to the
industry’s lobbying might.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
For a vital, timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my latest book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my new “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books
go to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.